A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial records, Diane Van Wie, Series 34 FA373
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Subject Files, 1953-1973; 02; 9 document box(es)
  - Capitol Story Booklet (Box 19, Folder 432)
    Lists of people receiving a copy of "Capitol Story" with cover letter 1964. Governor's cabinet list. A forward for the book "Capitol Story." Newspaper clippings on two mysteries about carvings in the Capitol Building. Letters regarding the book "Capitol Story" 1962-64. Photocopied pages from the book. Photocopied document about the laying of the cornerstone for the Capitol. An excerpt from the "New York Herald" June 25, 1871 about the laying of the cornerstone. Photocopied sections of the book "Capitol Story". "Chronological History of the New State Capitol" Laws and Proceedings connected to the building as well as a description of the building and a list of members of legislature (photocopied booklet) 1879. Annual report of the New Capitol Commissioners 1870. Cuyler Reynolds account of the new Capitol 1899-1900. Letters and memos concerning tours of the Capitol 1962. An appraisal of oil pointings in the Executive Chambers, State Capitol, Albany, New York. Memos regarding the distribution of the book "Capitol Story" 1964. Newspaper clipping with a picture of the Capitol. A memo concerning a Mr. Morrill who wants to sell two paintings by R. Sheridan to Nelson Rockefeller 1963. A list of Governors with portraits in the Capitol Building.
  - Capitol Story Booklet (Box 19, Folder 433)
  - City University Income Fund, undated (Box 19, Folder 434)
    A proposal for the "Ohrenstein Bill."
  - Civil Defense (Box 19, Folder 435)
    A resolution of the Civil Defense Committee on Fallout Protection from Nuclear Weapons August 5, 1959. A report of the Special Committee on Civil Defense of the Governors' Conference. A draft letter for the Governor's signature to all Governors transmitting the resolution adopted by the State Defense Council. An outline for Governor Rockefeller's speech at Governors' Conference. A letter to Governor Rockefeller discussing the need for a plan to protect U. S. citizens from nuclear fallout July 15, 1959. A letter to the Governor from Robert L. McManus urging a press conference to divert the interest of the attention on the press from the defense council. A letter regarding the development of a fallout protection program from Robert L. McManus, October 9, 1961. A memorandum to the Governor "Shelter Provision in State Financed Housing" concerning fallout shelters, October 13, 1961. A program calling for the construction of fallout shelters for consideration by the New York State Defense Council. Estimates for the cost of the Fallout Shelter Program as of October 6, 1961. A memo to the Governor about the financing of the Fallout Shelter Program, October 13, 1961. Estimates of the cost for the Fallout Shelter Program, October 16, 1961. Appropriations and expenses for the Fallout Shelter Program, March 11, 1960. An interview with Governor Rockefeller about his views towards nuclear testing, October 22, 1959. List of press releases. An interview with Governor Rockefeller about American troops in Western Europe, October 22, 1959. A report of the Fallout Shelter Program in state buildings, 1952. Civil defense chronological chart, July, 1959 - October, 1959.
  - Brief Highlights of New York Civil Liberties Union Report on The Ocean Hill-Brownsville School Controversy - "The Burden of Blame", October 10, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 436)
  - Civil Rights File, 1960-1962 (Box 19, Folder 437)
    Memorandums on a proposed conference on civil rights in Albany, December, 1960. A memo concerning discrimination, November 27, 1960. Memo to the Governor about the Federal Literacy Test Legislation, May 9, 1962. Proposed legislation that would outlaw literacy tests for federal elections, May 8, 1962. Memo on Governor Rockefeller's statement on the Hill-Burton Hospital Construction Law. Press conference, June 12, 1962. Notes following the meeting with Commissioner George Fowler, November 27, 1962.
  - Cold Spring, January 24, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 438)
    A list of figures for the value assessment of Cold Spring.
  - Colt .45 (Gift from Montana Centennial Commission), 1964 (Box 19, Folder 439)
    Material regarding a Colt .45 Governor Rockefeller received as a gift from The Montana Centennial Commission.
  - Committee for A Better New York City Government, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 440)
    A list of organizations and money disbursement.
  - Community Development Program Summary, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 441)
  - Compensation of Crime Victim - Outline of Proposed Bill (Box 19, Folder 442)
  - Con Edison, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 443)
    A copy of a prepared testimony in connection with the Federal Power Commission (FPC) hearings on Con Edison's Cornwall Project.
  - Condon-Wadlin Committee (Box 19, Folder 444)
    Handwritten notes outline of committee's' recommendations.
  - 1938 Constitutional Convention, April 5 to July 5, 1938 (Box 19, Folder 445)
    A list of meetings of the Constitutional Convention including short summaries of what was accomplished.
  - Constitutional Convention, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 446)
    Memorandum on the legal aspects of the election of the delegates at large to the Constitutional Convention, December 20, 1966.
  - Constitutional Convention, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 447)
    Mailing list of delegates who are members of the Temporary State Commission on Constitutional Convention. Suggestions to spark interest in the Constitutional Convention to the Governor from Attorney General Lefkowitz. An outline of opening statements for Governor Rockefeller at the January 25, 1967 New York State Constitutional Convention. A list of delegates at large and district delegates (key delegates, important delegates and very important delegates) at the Convention as well as a short list of proposed amendments adopted and defeated, December 19, 1966. A memo with proposed agenda for meeting with Constitutional Convention delegates, January 12, 1967.
  - Constitutional Convention, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 448)
    Material concerning the constitutional convention including drafts of opening speeches, statements and proposed amendments for the New York Constitution 1967. Constitutional Convention weekly reports, 1967.
  - Constitutional Convention, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 449)
  - Coordinated Transportation Policy, Planning and Programs, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 450)
    A solution to the problems of transportation demands a comprehensive, unified approach to the total transportation system. A report stating the need for more and expanded airports. A report calling for mass transportation in New York City and upstate. A report on railroad availability for New York. A report calling for more highway construction and maintenance. Summary of highway and parkway program New York State, 1967-68, 1971-72. "Transportation is Progress" a program to give New York better highways, better mas transportation, and better airports, 1967. The Transportation Bond Issue, a report with benefits.
  - Council on Foreign Relations, 1969 (Box 20, Folder 451)
    A booklet: "American Dilemma in Vietnam" - a report on the views of leading citizens in thirty-three cities. Council on foreign relations - discussion group on Latin America, third meeting, 1969, list of people who attended.
  - Council of Parks (Box 20, Folder 452)
    Memorandum concerning reappointments and appointments, May 12, 1967.
  - Council 50 (New York State Employees Council #50) (Box 20, Folder 453)
    A press release by the Council denouncing Governor Rockefeller for his stance on civil service jobs for the retarded, June 14, 1965.
  - Court Reorganization, 1959 (Box 20, Folder 454)
    A passage about court reorganization.
  - Courts - Terms Expiring, 1966 (Box 20, Folder 455)
    A list of members of Judicial divisions and their term expirations, 1966.
  - Preliminary Summary of Crime Control and Public Safety Proposals, undated (Box 20, Folder 456)
  - Council "What is Culture?" Report, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 457)
  - Committee on Department of Defense Organization, 1953 (Box 20, Folder 458)
    Questions to be included in discussions with witnesses before the Committee.
  - Demonstration Cities, 1966 (Box 20, Folder 459)
    Outline of a paper proposing a State Demonstration City and Metropolitan Development program making use of existing State Housing Finance Agency to get started immediately on these needed metropolitan projects. 1966.
  - Desalinization, 1965 (Box 20, Folder 460)
    Letters to the Governor suggesting the addition of a desalinization plant at the Indian Point power plant.
  - District Delegates to the Constitutional, 1966 (Box 20, Folder 461)
    Name list with Senate districts.
  - Debt Service Charges, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 462)
  - Division of Urban Affairs, 1966 (Box 20, Folder 463)
    A proposal for the establishment of a Division of Urban Affairs, January 4, 1966.
  - Eavesdropping (Box 20, Folder 464)
    A program to conform the State's eavesdropping law to the federal law.
  - Economic Growth - United States and New York, 1962 (Box 20, Folder 465)
    Comparative statistics, New York State and United States.
  - Education, 1960 (Box 20, Folder 466)
    Background education sheets on education (Defense Education Program, Federal aid for school construction, federally impacted areas). Statement on educational finance.
  - Studies of Public School Support, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 467)
    A report of studies of public school support 1967 series: The urban education crisis: Some fiscal consideration. A letter to Governor Rockefeller: Proposed plans for increased revenue for educational purposes. Rockland County School Boards Association Presentation to Honorable Nelson A. Rockefeller, Governor of the State of New York, November 20, 1968. Presentation to Nelson A. Rockefeller,Governor of the State of New York by the Nassau and Suffolk School Boards Association, November 20, 1968. A presentation to the Governor from the Westchester County School Boards Association, November 20, 1968.
  - Federal-State Education Act of 1969 - A Comprehensive Block Grant Welfare Program (Outline) (Box 20, Folder 468)
  - Education Committee, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 469)
    Staff arrangements of the Bundy Committee, April 19, 1967. A memo concerning the first meeting of the Bundy Committee, April 6, 1967. A memo concerning preliminary considerations of the second annual meeting of Education Commission of the States, March 14, 1967. A memo to the Governor about an employing firm called "Nelson's Associates".
  - Economic Outlook for 1968 in New York State (Box 20, Folder 470)
    An essay about the economic outlook for New York State in 1968.
  - Fall Out Shelter Program (Civil Defense), 1960 (Box 20, Folder 471)
    An amendment to the New York State Defense Emergency Act, March 2, 1960. A letter to Nelson Rockefeller supporting his fallout shelter program from Edward Teller, February 25, 1960. A memo to the Governor with short descriptions of the civil defense program of Sweden, Denmark and Switzerland, March 4, 1960. A report to the Governor from the Committee on Fallout Protection, February 15, 1960.
  - Federalist Papers and Thumbull Society, 1965 (Box 20, Folder 472)
  - Our State's Finances (Box 20, Folder 473)
    Handwritten notes. "Abuses in unemployment insurance" - Proposals to existing laws concerning voluntary quitters and voluntary retirees, December 30, 1959. A report on the finances of New York State.
  - Foreign Policy, undated (Box 20, Folder 474)
    A report on the relationships between the United States and other nations.
  - President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board, 1969 (Box 20, Folder 475)
    Press release - the President issued an executive order establishing the President's foreign intelligence advisory board, March 20, 1969. Memos and letter concerning the President's foreign intelligence advisory board.
  - Garbage Strike, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 476)
    Letters, memos, newspaper clippings, press releases, and handwritten notes on the department of sanitation strike in New York City, 1968.
  - Gifts for Auction to GOP Groups, 1965-1966 (Box 21, Folder 477)
    A thank you letter concerning a silver dish as a gift for a fund-raising auction, February 2, 1966. A thank you letter concerning a silver dish to the Association of Young Republicans for "Appreciation Night", August 19, 1965. A thank you letter concerning a wedding gift to Carol Intememan, Steuben glass bowl, August 10, 1965.
  - Governor's Committee on Public Employee Relations Final Report, 1966 (Box 21, Folder 478)
  - The Governor's Club, 1965 (Box 21, Folder 479)
    Governors Club list. Thank you note to Dean Alfange, August 5, 1965. Thank you letters to the Governor for the luncheon at the Governor's Club, 1965.
  - Hammarskjold Memorial Legislation, 1962 (Box 21, Folder 480)
    List of sponsors, members of the Senate finance committee, Assembly ways and means committee, and the Assembly rules committee.
  - Haryou - Act, 1965-1966 (Box 21, Folder 481)
    Narcotics Institute's budget summary 1965-66. Summary of the proposal of the Narcotics Institute program, 1965.
  - Department of Health - State Aid, 1969 (Box 21, Folder 482)
    Formula revision for Department of Health - state aid, Department of Mental Hygiene - state aid, City University - state aid, Community College State capital aid, Community Colleges - State operating aid, education - state aid, state aid for public assistance and care medicaid - limit dental benefits, state aid for public assistance and care medicaid - reduction in professional fees, state aid for public assistance and care medicaid - eliminate hospital and nursing home rate increases, state aid for public assistance and care medicaid - limit nursing home benefits, state aid for public assistance and care, and City University - Seek Programs.
  - Analysis of Health Department Proposal for Amendments on Title XIX, 1966 (Box 21, Folder 483)
    May 5, 1966 memo re: Analysis of Health Department proposal for amendments on Title XIX. Single state agency requirements for federal welfare administration.
  - Higher Education Recommendations (Box 21, Folder 484)
    A paper on higher education recommendations and a list of New York City Colleges and their funds available as of July 1, 1966.
  - Hudson River, 1965 (Box 21, Folder 485)
    A list of pros and cons of federal pollution control. Hudson River Drainage Basin - drainage basin requiring corrective action. Follow up items and principal action taken at meeting on coordination of Hudson River Valley activities, August 9, 1965.
  - The Hudson River Valley Commission (Compact Creating) Preamble (Box 21, Folder 486)
  - Hudson River Valley Commission (Compact with the Federal Government, New York and New Jersey), 1966 (Box 21, Folder 487)
    A chronology of the Hudson River Valley Commission. A memo concerning the Ottinger bill, September 2, 1966, including three major loopholes. A memo to the Governor concerning attacks on the Hudson River Valley Commission, August 3, 1966. A list of people attending the organizational meeting of the Hudson River Valley Commission, August 8, 1966; memos, letters, and statements concerning the bill HR 13508. A memo with information on the background of the former Hudson River Valley Commission, July 26, 1966. An act to encourage the development of the Hudson River.
  - Human Rights, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 488)
    A letter and memo regarding a vital meeting of the Commission of Human Rights.
  - Increased Mortgage Recording Tax, 1969 (Box 21, Folder 489)
    A proposal that would increase the tax on the recording of real property mortgages and earmark the proceeds of the increase for regional transportation authorities.
  - Inter-American Affairs, 1959 (Box 21, Folder 490)
    Memos and correspondence concerning the Institute for Inter-American Affairs.
  - Interstate Regional Planning Commission, undated (Box 21, Folder 491)
    A compact to develop an Interstate Regional Planning Commission, this would establish a 21 member commission, from New York, New Jersey, Connecticut and the Federal Government, to review, make comments, and recommendations on applications for federal aid and grants. A Mid-Atlantic States air pollution compact to create an Interstate Air Pollution Control Commission.
  - Job Development Authority, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 492)
    A memo concerning a joint resolution by the 1968 legislature to increase the amount of state guaranteed bonds of the Job Development Authority from $50 million to $150 million and to extend five to seven years, 1968.
  - Kidney Disease, undated (Box 21, Folder 493)
    General memo on the creation of a state program to combat kidney disease.
  - Legislative Appropriation Reductions (Including Reappropriations), undated (Box 21, Folder 494)
  - Legislative Program and Political Mileage Therefrom (Box 21, Folder 495)
    A memo with suggestions for the 1961 legislative program.
  - Legislative Summary, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 496)
    A draft for the legislative summary in 1960.
  - Legislation - Condon-Wadlin Law, undated (Box 21, Folder 497)
    A revision of the Condon-Wadlin law.
  - Library Aid, 1966 (Box 21, Folder 498)
    A list of program bills and present laws in regard to library aid.
  - Lincoln Center, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 499)
    The New York State Council on Architecture - Panel of commentators, a list of the commentators. A cover letter regarding a new balcony in Lincoln Center. A map of the Lincoln Center area, 1968.
  - Lincoln Square, 1958-1959 (Box 21, Folder 500)
    Correspondence regarding Lincoln Center, the Lincoln Square Project, and a meeting concerning Lincoln Center.
  - Lindsay, Mayor John V., 1966 (Box 21, Folder 501)
    A letter to the Governor from Mayor Lindsay with proposals to make changes in New York City and State policy also adjustments in state aid to the City. Correspondence concerning the Lincoln Park Plan. A copy of an outline for the Lindsay Campaign position on transportation. A transcript of an interview with Mayor Lindsay. A text of testimony given by John Lindsay, prepared for delivery before the Joint Committee on Rules, March 10, 1966. Statement to the legislature of the State of New York in support of a tax program for New York City, 1966.
  - List of Files Store in Cellar - New York State, 1959-1965 (Box 21, Folder 502)
  - Dr. Logan, Sandy Ray - Material for Phone Calls, 1966 (Box 21, Folder 503)
    Memos concerning committees, members of the committees and their salaries.
  - Long Island Railroad, 1969 (Box 21, Folder 504)
    A draft reply to the Nickerson Telegram regarding aid to the Long Island Rail Road. Draft of a position paper on the removal of Dr. William T. Ronan as Chairman of the Metropolitan Transportation Authority. Long Island Railroad M-1 railway car training program - a proposal. Handwritten notes on the Long Island Railroad problem. Memos concerning the conditions at the Long Island Railroad. A letter to the Governor concerning the problems at the Long Island Railroad. First instance capital construction appropriation. Newspaper clippings of the LIRR's track record. Newspaper clippings on the Long Island Railroad.
  - Televoice - Hunger Campus Disorder, 1969 (Box 21, Folder 505)
    A statement from Governor Rockefeller about hunger in New York state college campuses.
  - Magazine Articles - Article for "Foreign Affairs", 1960 (Box 21, Folder 506)
    An outline of the article for "Foreign Affairs." The article for "Foreign Affairs."
  - Magazine Articles "North American Newspaper Alliance", 1968 (Box 22, Folder 507)
  - Mandated Programs (Box 22, Folder 508)
    State mandated programs effecting city budgets. Mandatory legislation pending before the 1966 New York State legislature opposed by the County Officers Association.
  - Mansion - New Estimate for Reconstruction, May 10, 1961 (Box 22, Folder 509)
  - Mansion Budget, 1961 (Box 22, Folder 510)
    Estimates for construction of the new mansion and reconstruction at the old mansion.
  - Mass Transportation Authorities Act (Box 22, Folder 511)
  - Medallions, 1964-1965 (Box 22, Folder 512)
    Memos concerning medallions distributed to different committees and commissions, 1965. Acknowledgements of orders for medallions. A letter requesting a medallion for Dr. William J. Ronan with certificate. Letters ordering medallions, 1965. Lists of committee members receiving medallions, 1965. Lists of committee members receiving medallions. Press release, Governor Rockefeller announced that he was putting together a three person committee to develop plans for a New York State memorial for Herbert H. Lehman, 1964. Press release, Governor Rockefeller announced the creation of a citizens committee to examine widely into helping welfare recipients become self-sufficient and halting the rising spiral of relief costs, 1965. Press release, Governor Rockefeller announced the appointment of a seven member committee of prominent citizens to make a study of hospital costs and the alignment of state responsibilities in the hospital field, 1964. Press release, Governor Rockefeller announced the Committee to make Recommendations on the Future State of the Long Island Railroad, 1964. Press release, Governor Rockefeller announced the creation of the Hudson River Valley Commission, 1965.
  - Medical Care for the Aged, 1962 (Box 22, Folder 513)
    NAR notes on Medical Care for the Aged.
  - Medicaid, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 514)
    Communications critical of the State Medicaid Program. Newspaper stories on medicare. Memo discussing progress in medicaid, welfare, education and a conclusion.
  - Medical Assistance for the Needy, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 515)
    Reports, statements, memos, handwritten notes, interviews and an act on social welfare and medical assistance for the needy, 1966. A memo on additional state aid and other income for New York City, May 17, 1966. A letter to Senate Majority leader Earl W. Brydges and Speaker Anthony J. Travia requesting that the medical assistance for the needy program not be passed, May 17, 1966. An editorial "Rockefeller Haters Unwise: Democrats Certain to Benefit."
  - Mental Retardation Statement, 1965 (Box 22, Folder 516)
    Facts on programs in New York State on the mentally retarded. A memo regarding the draft of NAR's statement on the mentally retarded, September 11, 1965. A statement from Governor Rockefeller on the mentally retarded, January 25, 1965.
  - Metropolitan Council on Housing, 1965 (Box 22, Folder 517)
    A memo on a meeting of the Metropolitan Council on Housing. Proposals to the New York legislature from the Metropolitan Council on Housing on tenant safety and low rent housing. Newspaper clippings on urban renewal in New York City, 1965.
  - Metropolitan Transportation (Brochure: A Program for Action) (Box 22, Folder 518)
    Metropolitan Transportation - brochure: A program for action, a list of bills involving Metropolitan Transportation and status, May 13, 1968.
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 22, Folder 519)
    A memo with appointments to miscellaneous committees, and commissions.
  - Model City Applications, 1968 (Box 22, Folder 520)
    A list of approved model city applications. A special message to the legislature on the creation of a New York State Urban Development Corporation. An outline of a plan for the New York State Urban Development Corporation. Legislation to create a Corporation for Urban Research and Development. Legislation to create the Urban Development Guarantee Fund of New York, 1968.
  - Mt. Vernon School, undated (Box 22, Folder 521)
    A report: A Mount Vernon, New York, Answer for the Renaissance of Education in the American City.
  - Museum Exhibits in the Cultural Center, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 522)